Chapter 15. Chowder.
It was quite late in the evening when the little moss came snugly to anchor,
and Quequake and I went ashore, so we could attend to no business that day, at
least none but a supper and a bed. The landlord of the Spouter Inn had
recommended us to his cousin, Hosea Hussy of the Tripots, whom he asserted
to be the proprietor of one of the bestkept hotels in all Nantucket. And
moreover, he had assured us that cousin Hosea, as he called him, was famous for
his chowters. In short, he plainly hinted that we could not possibly do
better than tripot lock at the tripods.
But the directions he had given us about keeping a yellow warehouse on our
starboard hand till we opened a white church to the Larbird, and then keeping
that on the Larbird hand till we made a corner three points to the starboard,
and that done. then asked the first man we met where the place was. These
crooked directions of his very much puzzled us at first, especially as at
the outset Quiquake insisted that the yellow warehouse, our first point of
departure, must be left on the lar hand, whereas I had understood Peter coffin to
say it was on the starboard.
However, by dent of beating about a little in the dark, and now and then
knocking up a peaceable inhabitant to inquire the way, we at last came to
something which there was no mistaking.
Two enormous wooden pots, painted black, and suspended by ass's ears, swung from
the cross trees of an old top mast, planted in front of an old doorway. The
horns of the cross trees were sawed off on the other side, so that this old top
mass looked not a little like the gallows. Perhaps I was oversensitive to
such impressions at the time, but I could not help staring at this gallows
with vague misgiving. A sort of cick was in my neck as I gazed up to the two
remaining horns. Yes, two of them. One for Quiquake and one for me. It's
ominous, thinks I, a coffin, my inkeeper, upon landing in my first
whailing port. tombstones staring at me in the whaleman's chapel and here a
gallows and a pair of prodigious black pots too. Are these lass throwing out
oblique hints touching toe?
I was called from these reflections by the sight of a freckled woman with
yellow hair and a yellow gown, standing in the porch of the inn under a dull red
lamp swinging there that looked much like an injured eye, and carrying on a
brisk scolding with a man in a purple woolen shirt. "Get along with ye," she
said to the man, "or I'll be combing you." "Come on, Quiquake," said I. "All
right, there is Mrs. Hussy." And so it turned out, Mr. Hosea Hussie being from
home but leaving Mrs. Hussie entirely competent to attend to all his affairs.
Upon making known our desires for supper and a bed, Mrs. Hussie, postponing
further scolding for the present, ushered us into a little room, and
seating us at a table spread with the relics of a recently concluded repast
turned round to us and said, "Clam or cod?" "What's that about cods, ma'am?"
said I, with much politeness. Clam or cod? She repeated. A clam for supper. A
cold clam. Is that what you mean, Mrs.
Hussy? Says I. But that's a rather cold and clammy reception in the wintertime,
ain't it, Mrs. Hussy? But being in a great hurry to resume scolding the man
in the purple shirt, who was waiting for it in the entry, and seeming to hear
nothing but the word clam, Mrs. Hussy hurried towards an open door leading to
the kitchen and balling out clam for two disappeared.
"Quig," said I, "Do you think that we can make out a supper for us both on one
clam?"
However, a warm and savory steam from the kitchen served to belly the
apparently cheerless prospect before us.
But when that smoking chowder came in, the mystery was delightfully explained.
"Oh, sweet friends, hearken to me. It was made of small juicy clams scarcely
bigger than hazelnuts, mixed with pounded ship biscuit and salted pork cut
up into little flakes, the whole enriched with butter and plentifully
seasoned with pepper and salt. Our appetites being sharpened by the frosty
voyage, and in particular Quequake, seeing his favorite fishing food before
him, and the chowder being surpassingly excellent, we dispatched it with great
expedition. When leaning back a moment, and bethinking me of Mrs. Tussy's clam
and cod announcement. I thought I would try a little experiment. Stepping to the
kitchen door, I uttered the word cod with great emphasis and resumed my seat.
In a few moments the savory steam came forth again, but with a different
flavor, and in good time a fine cod chowder was placed before us. We resumed
business, and while pllying our spoons in the bowl, thinks I to myself, I
wonder now if this here has any effect on the head. What's that stoaltifying
saying about chowder-headed people? But look, Quiquake, ain't that a live eel in
your bowl? Where's your harpoon?
Fishiest of all fishy places was the tripods, which welld deserved its name,
for the pots there were always boiling chowters. Chowder for breakfast and
chowder for dinner and chowder for supper till you began to look for
fishbones coming through your clothes.
The area before the house was paved with clamshells. Mrs. Hussie wore a polished
necklace of codfish vertebrae, and Hosea Hussie had his account books bound in
superior old shark skin. There was a fishy flavor to the milk, too, which I
could not at all account for, till one morning, happening to take a stroll
along the beach among some fisherman's boats, I saw Hosea's brindled cow
feeding on fish remnants, and marching along the sand with each foot in a cod's
decapitated head, looking very slipshot, I assure you.
Supper concluded, we received a lamp and directions from Mrs. Hussy concerning
the nearest way to bed. But as Quiqu Quig was about to proceed me up the
stairs, the lady reached forth her arm and demanded his harpoon. She allowed no
harpoon in her chambers. "Why not?" said I. "Every true whaleman sleeps with his
harpoon. But why not?" "Because it's dangerous," says she. Ever since young
Stigs, coming from that unfortunate voyage of his, when he was gone four
years and a half with only three barrels of, was found dead in my first floor
back with his harpoon in his side. Ever since then, I allow no borders to take
such dangerous weapons in their rooms at night. So, Mr. Quiquake, for she had
learned his name, I will just take this here iron and keep it for you until
morning. But the chowder, clam or cod tomorrow for breakfast, men. Both, says
I. And let's have a couple of smoked herring by way of variety.